בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today's דף daf is יט. yud-tet. 15th
day of the עומר, Omer, we're halfway there. It's פסח שני. Pesach
Sheini. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
We are the very last line of יח עמוד ב. yud-ches amud-beis.
We had laid some of the basic principles of the act of
מעילה, Me'ilah,
and the key is number one that we learned it from we
said מעילה Me'ilah is שינוי, shinoy, which I've translated as sort of
diverting, to divert something away from where it belongs or its true
purpose. And as we've been talking, there are two types of מעילה.
Me'ilah. There's a sense of like the stealing, of taking away from
הקדש, hekdesh, and then there's the other of deriving benefit. The גמרא
Gemara actually learned it from two פסוקים psukim of מעילה. Me'ilah. One
is the woman who commits adultery, where the Torah describes as תמעול
מעל באשה, timal maal b'isha, to trespass against her husband. And the
other is where בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel worship עבודה זרה avodah zarah
and they're מועל mo'el in God. And as תוספות Tosafot explains there,
the first one was basically the sharing of the sexual pleasure that
should be between her and her husband, sharing with another
person, becomes of another man, is the model for the מעילה Me'ilah
of deriving benefit from הקדש hekdesh that does not belong to the
layperson. It's the benefit that belongs to הקדש. hekdesh. The other idea
of worshipping עבודה זרה avodah zarah is we often talk about like
who בני ישראל Bnei Yisroel are belong to God, the concept that
the people are the people of the God that they worship. So
the idea of going to another God is like taking away from
God's possession and placing themselves under the control of another God is
the type of מעילה Me'ilah of taking away from הקדש hekdesh and
taking possession away from הקדש. hekdesh.
Does that same thing about a woman and her husband work the
reverse way?
No, because we're talking about a polygamous I know, we missed רי"ף
Rif yesterday too. We're talking about a polygamous society, so the exclusive
nature is only one way. But as I said, we will have
plenty of chance to talk about that when we get to סוטה.
Sotah. Right. Okay, so anyway, but then the other point is is
that interestingly, as מעילה Me'ilah is different from other things, is is
that it combines with over long periods of time, because it's a
פרוטה prutah a little bit today, a little bit later, because it's
not like an act of eating that has to take place within
a few minutes. It's a taking away and therefore that can sort
of culminate. It's the total amount that is benefited from at the
end or that's taken away at the end. And even combining what
you did with what somebody else did, again, if somebody else did
it on their own volition then those are different acts. But if
you, let's say, ate some something that's הקדש hekdesh and you put
some, anointed some on somebody's skin, so although that person is the
one that receives the benefit, since you're the one that took it
away, that took the benefit even though you weren't the recipient of
it, those combine for the minimum amount for the פרוטה, prutah, and
again, even over a period of time. So there's a lot of
ways in which it's not sort of like a normal act of
eating or normal act of benefit, because this concept of מעילה Me'ilah
is different than those concepts per se. So that's some of the
base principles we said yesterday, and now we continue at the bottom
of יח עמוד ב.
yud-ches amud-beis. Okay. Like let's say I take הקדש hekdesh flour, right?
And then it's in my possession, I don't do anything with it,
but then it becomes all wormy and stuff like that.
Then... That's like if you damage הקדש. hekdesh. So פגם ולא נהנה
pagam ve'lo neheneh is also not מעילה. Me'ilah. Okay, there has to
be the deriving of benefit.
But then what am I? I'm just over a לא תעשה? lo
ta'aseh? I only have to pay back? Yeah, you have to pay
back just the principal, right?
Right. Yes. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says, bottom of יח
עמוד ב, yud-ches amud-beis, אם חטא im acheit אמה דתרומה, amai d'terumah,
very last line of יח עמוד ב, yud-ches amud-beis, אם חטא im
acheit אמה דתרומה, amai d'terumah, עד שיצא מן הקודש לחול. ad sheyeitzei
min hakodesh lechol. Maybe because the other model we learned was not
only from the עבודה זרה avodah zarah and the סוטה, Sotah, but
the other model we learned was from תרומה terumah where it also
says חטא, cheit, and תרומה terumah is analogous that if somebody eats
תרומה terumah they pay back the כהן kohen plus a fifth. So
there's certain parallels. And there we learn out the key principle we
learned out there, by the way, was that it was הנאה hana'ah
that also came with the act of deriving benefit also caused some
damage in the thing itself, like the act of eating. Like you
don't just derive benefit without any impact, you derive benefit and it
damages the thing itself and that came at the same time, in
the same object that was damaged and so on. And that's another
principle, that something that normally when benefit is derived some damage, the
thing itself suffers some loss or some damage, some wear and tear,
that is a required part of the act of מעילה. Me'ilah. So
now it's saying, oh, if we're learning out from תרומה terumah though,
why don't we say it has to be totally like תרומה? terumah?
עד שיצא מן הקודש לחול, ad sheyeitzei min hakodesh lechol, only if
you take something that was תרומה terumah and it's קודש kodesh and
use it for חול, chol, for totally
lay purposes. But transferring from one aspect of קודש kodesh to another
would not be the דין din of eating תרומה. terumah. So מן
הקודש לקודש, min hakodesh lekodesh, let's say you transfer from one type
of קודש kodesh to another. כגון, Kegon, what would that example be?
לקח קיני זבים בקיני זבות. Lakach kinei zavim bekinei zavos. and קיני
יולדות. kinei yoldot. Let's say you went ahead and there was money
set aside
for... for בדק הבית, Bedek habayis, money set aside for a donation
to the temple treasury. And instead what did you do with it?
You went ahead and you used it to buy a קרבן. korban.
So it's not like you took some money from הקדש hekdesh to
buy for yourself a TV. Wow, okay, I took some money that
belonged to הקדש hekdesh but I brought a קרבן korban with it.
Okay, so maybe that's not מעילה me'ilah because it's just diverting to
another הקדש hekdesh purpose, not to a lay purpose, right? And so...
wait, so your קיני זבים, kinei zavin, קיני זבות, kinei zavot, you
said...
is money? No, no, you buy birds for your קרבנות, korbanos, but
where do you get the money? You took הקדש'ס hekdesh's money, money
that was in the temple treasury that was being... going to be
used for operating funds or going to be used for repairs, and
you said, 'Okay, I took it.' But hey, you know, it's like
people have nice ways of
rationalizing, right? 'Alright, I stole but I gave money to צדקה.' tzedakah.
You know, so, 'Okay, I took it from הקדש hekdesh but I
brought a קרבן korban with it.'
There's nothing new under the sun.
Exactly, so maybe that's not
מעילה. me'ilah. Okay. ובשלוש שקלו? u'veshalosh shekelo? We're getting there. ובשלוש שקלו,
u'veshalosh shekelo, or let's say, now this is even a lesser maybe
concern of a violation: you have to give a שקל shekel to
the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash each year. Now you would sometimes, not
only be a coin, half שקל, shekel, excuse me, a good point.
Now let's say it would not only be a coin, let's say
you would have to... exactly... let's say you would have to weigh
out, you know, on a scale, right? How much, you know, to
make sure you had the right amount of weight of your various
of your coins. Well, let's say the counterweight you used something of
הקדש. hekdesh. You're not even stealing, you're just deriving benefit from it,
you're using it as a counterweight, right? You understand on a balance
scale. Okay, but you still can't derive benefit from הקדש. hekdesh. 'Oh,
but I'm using it for a good מצוה mitzvah purpose, I'm deriving
benefit in order to weigh out my שקל shekel to the בית
המקדש.' Beis Hamikdash. Or
והביא חטאתו ואשמו מן ההקדש. vehevi chataso veashamo min hahekdesh. It's interesting
the way it mixes some of these different ones, like why differentiate
the קרבן korban of the birds and this, or I take the
money that was הקדש hekdesh money and I bring a חטאת chatas
offering. And now, כיון שהוציא מעל, keivan shehotzi mo'al, as soon as
you spent that money you were מועל mo'el as soon as you
spent it. Now what does it mean spent it? דברי רבי שמעון.
divrei Rabi Shimon. רבי יהודה אומר עד שיזרק הדם. Rabi Yehuda omer
ad sheyizarak hadam. So you have to be זורק הדם. zorek hadam.
Now what is that about? So that's another debate, which is that
where are you... when do you exempt yourself from your obligation of
your קרבן? korban? If you're obligated in a חטאת chatas or an
אשם, asham, when are you... when do you exempt yourself from the
obligation? Now we would normally assume like רבי יהודה Rabi Yehuda says,
you exempt yourself once there's זריקת הדם, zerikas hadam, once the קרבן
korban is good. But actually רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon says that you
exempt yourself once you bring your קרבן korban into the בית המקדש,
Beis Hamikdash, which is quite fascinating, even before it's brought. 'Okay, I
was פטור, patur, the קרבן korban is good, you know, I'm פטור,
patur, I brought it.' So here they're saying is as soon as
you... now again this is always the question, right? When by מעילה
me'ilah is it considered like you used it, you took possession of
it? So actually if I... so here they're saying once I brought
that into the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, whether it was זורק הדם,
zorek hadam, so I actually benefited, I exempted myself from my obligation,
then that would be מעילה, me'ilah, okay? המונה והבורח? hamoneh vehaboreiach? Yeah,
so this actually is interesting and the גמרא Gemara doesn't really fully
unpack this because, you know, why it gave specifically examples of זבין
zavin and זבות zavot and יולדות yoldot and חטאת chatas and אשם,
asham, which are obligatory קרבנות, korbanos, right? What if I took the
money and I brought an עולה olah with it, right? Aren't I
still like misusing הקדש hekdesh even though I didn't particularly derive benefit?
But you know what, maybe not, because although nobody said you did
a good thing, right, and one actually would wonder even if the
קרבן korban is sanctified because, you know, if it's not your money
and how did you exactly buy it and the קדושה kedushah wasn't
a קדושה kedushah of a קרבן korban and how did you transfer
and all those questions? So those are all good questions, but it
could be that remember, הקדש hekdesh is only if you're נהנה. neheneh.
So maybe if you used it and transferred it to an עולה
olah and it wasn't exempting you from an obligation, you know, maybe
that's not exactly considered הנאה, hana'ah, although other places the גמרא Gemara
does consider it to be הנאה. hana'ah. So and then the question
becomes the act of stealing. Well, how do you define, you know,
stealing of הקדש? hekdesh? We're going to get to... so it is
a good question like what exactly are the parameters here and why
is it limiting it to cases of satisfying an obligation? שקל shekel
is also by the way an obligation, right? It never gave an
example of sanctity... using it for another sanctity that wasn't a personal
obligation. So that is a good question and the גמרא... Gemara...
what? המונה והבורח? hamoneh vehaboreiach?
Yeah, it might be if you sort of stole it, you know,
and we're going to see, we're going to come up to the
next משנה mishnah on the עמוד ב amud beis of what moment
is defined of stealing from הקדש. hekdesh. You know, if this is
God's, if this is קדוש kadosh and it's God's here and if
it's God's, if it's in the temple treasury and it's God's everywhere,
God's is here, God's is there, right, so what defines the act
of stealing, right, of taking it away? So we'll talk about that,
that's coming up. So it could be... Okay, well be. Certainly if
there was an act of stealing, it should matter, right? But then,
but we're trying to frame it that no, the מעילה Me'ilah was
not the stealing. Then it wouldn't have been what you're using it
for later. Then it would have been the act of stealing. But
the מעילה Me'ilah was the using for a different purpose, diverting, and
not an act of stealing. I mean stealing does become a later
concept, but that's not the purpose here. So somehow we're talking that
the money was used for a קרבן Korban without that act of
stealing taking place or being relevant. Again, I'm not exactly sure what
that scenario is. And if that's true and the focus is more
on deriving benefit, we're limiting ourselves to cases where you use it
to satisfy an obligation where there's clear benefit. Okay, so that seems
to be, you know, how it's being structured here. But there really,
there was no discussion in the גמרא Gemara or in תוספות Tosafot
or in רבנו גרשום Rabbeinu Gershom and so on. So I haven't
seen if the אחרונים Achronim discuss this case more.
Anyway,
מהו כששהוציא? Mahu Keshehhotzi?
So again, that sounds like it means when you spend the money,
but רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot say that it basically means like
the classic position of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon when you bring the
קרבן Korban into the עזרה, Azarah, which is not the פשט Pshat
of those words כששהוציא. Keshehhotzi. So נמוקי יוסף Nimukei Yosef says
הוציא Hotzi means once I take it out from temple treasury,
which would be, which I would agree, would be the
פשט Pshat of those words and a natural thing to think. Anyway,
so there are definitely questions of the exact parameters of all of
this. And Michael's exactly correct, and it is worth again mentioning that
all these are cases of, you know, of obligation, of satisfying an
obligation. Anyway, maybe I would have even excluded those cases, because at
the end you're using it for another קודש Kodesh purpose. So תלמוד
לומר, Talmud Lomar, so the ברייתא Braisa says תימעול מעל מכל מקום.
Timoal Ma'al Mikol Makom. No, תימעול מעל Timoal Ma'al comes to tell
you under all circumstances, even if you are, you know, not using
it for your personal gain, even if you're just diverting it to
a different type of הקדש Hekdesh purpose. But again, it is worth
noting in this context that you are at least gaining in the
sense that you're using it to help you satisfy some obligation. Okay,
so now the גמרא Gemara is going to, that was a long
ברייתא Braisa that we had yesterday, and we end today. And now
the גמרא Gemara is going to unpack it a little bit. אמר
מר. Amar Mar. So the ברייתא Braisa starts the following way: נפש.
Nefesh. If a soul, like נפש כי תימעול מעל Nefesh Ki Timoal
Ma'al is the פסוק Pasuk in the תורה, Torah, if a soul
does an act of trespass. So it said, what does נפש Nefesh
mean? אחד יחיד ואחד נשיא ואחד משוח, Echad Yachid Ve'echad Nasi Ve'echad
Mashuach,
whether anybody, whether it's a lay person, or whether it's a נשיא,
Nasi, a king, whether it's a כהן גדול, Kohen Gadol, anybody's in
this פרשה. Parsha. Now why would I have had an הוה אמינא
Havah Amina otherwise? Let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. והאי לאו...
Ve'hai Lav... so the גמרא Gemara says, שיכול מאי? Sheyachol Mai?
It's again, here you see the language is not the standard in
other places. But anyway, meaning, what would I have thought? Meaning שיכול
מאי? Sheyachol Mai? Sort of like, you know, what would I have,
what would I have thought? Why would I have thought to exclude
them? פשיטא, Pshita, of course, נפש כתיב. Nefesh Kasiv. No, נפש, Nefesh,
of course. Why would I even need a דרשה Drasha to tell
me everybody's included? No, מהו דתימא, Mah Du Teima, I might have
thought, אמר רחמנא Amar Rachmana ואשר יתן ממנו על זר. Va'asher Yiten
Mimenu Al Zar. Remember we learned about the שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishchah
a long time ago, not even in this מסכת. Masechet. Anyway, it
says that if
you put from it on a זר, Zar, on a foreign person,
והאי לאו זר הוא, Ve'hai Lav Zar Hu, and at least the,
and the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol and the king are not a
זר Zar because the כהן גדול Kohen Gadol you would anoint with
the שמן המשחה, Shemen Hamishchah, kings you would sometimes anoint with שמן
המשחה Shemen Hamishchah if there was some, you know, debate over the
מלכות. Malchus. נשיא Nasi is interpreted, yeah, I know, but it's, you're
correct, but it's interpreted by חז"ל Chazal in the contemporary context, their
contemporary, you know, the post-period of the תורה, Torah, which you had
נשיאים Nesi'im for tribes, you know, they, they translated into the context
of a king, of a political leader, a
political leader and a spiritual leader.
Right,
so the נשיא Nasi is a political leader, but after the period
of individual of heads of tribes, the political leader was the king,
you know, so that's how they translate. But you're, you're right. I
mean there are discussions sometimes about נשיא Nasi being other types of
political heads, not limited to that of the king. So but here
specifically it is king because it's tapping into the idea that the
king would be anointed with the שמן המשחה. Shemen Hamishchah. And then
there was some discussion that if you put the שמן המשחה Shemen
Hamishchah even after the act of anointing on a king or כהן
גדול, Kohen Gadol, maybe they would not violate because they were not
considered a זר, Zar, they were not totally foreign to the, you
know, to the ability to have שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishchah on them.
So because of that, you wouldn't
mean for any other?
Well, so that's, that's how they're structuring the הוה אמינא. Havah Amina.
Okay, so והאי לאו זר הוא, Ve'hai Lav Zar Hu, these are
not זר, Zar, דאמשח בגביה, De'imshach Be'gavaya, they were already anointed with
the שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishchah and there is that discussion in כריתות
Kerisos whether if a כהן גדול Kohen Gadol who you anoint with
שמן המשחה, Shemen Hamishchah, is he considered a זר Zar or
not? So I would have said, so that's a similar idea. Using
something that's הקדש Hekdesh and the שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishchah they might
be excluded, maybe by מעילה Me'ilah as well. קא משמע לן Ka
Mashma Lan that they're not. Okay, so that's the first point out.
Tell me about the שמן המשחה Shemen Hamishchah now if you know.
I would have said more פשט Pshat is the fact that in
that context there's, by when it speaks about the חטאת, Chatas, which
is right before that, right on. And it speaks about אשר נשיא
יחטא, Asher Nasi Yecheta, you know,
what's the, what's the פסוק? Pasuk?
Right,
so there are distinctions by them, by other קרבנות, korbanos, but anyway
the גמרא Gemara here is focusing on the שמן ומשחה. shemen umishcha.
Okay, now that was point one of the ברייתא. braisa. Now the
major point of the ברייתא braisa was the models of סוטה, sota,
עבודה זרה, avoda zara, and תרומה. teruma. Now the גמרא Gemara is
just going to really paraphrase what we learned from that. ואקיש רחמנא
לסוטה עבודת כוכבים ותרומה. Va'akish rachmana lesota avodas kochavim uteruma. Now מעילה
me'ila was connected to סוטה sota and עבודה זרה avoda zara because
it uses the words מעילה me'ila in those, and תרומה teruma from
חטא חטא cheit cheit and a comparison. לסוטה, Lesota, what do we
learn from סוטה? sota? דאף על גב דלא פגים, De'af al gav
delo pagim, because by סוטה sota there's the idea of of you
know like I said her her you know sharing her the sexual
pleasure with another man. So there you have the idea of deriving
benefit from הקדש hekdesh that doesn't belong to you. And that's a
case where the thing here, presumably the woman, isn't isn't injured, you
know, isn't somehow
isn't you know so doesn't suffer a loss. So that would be
the concept of מעילה. me'ila. Sometimes מעילה me'ila is deriving benefit even
if no loss occurred to the object. The משנה mishna distinguished between
two types of scenarios. One is where an object is normally used
in which which when the normal benefiting of the object does is
not accompanied with some loss in the object. So for example it
says like wearing a golden necklace or drinking from a golden goblet.
So you derive benefit without any loss occurring to the object. So
there just the act of benefit alone is מעילה, me'ila, as opposed
to scenarios where it usually is accompanied wear and tear, driving a
car, wearing clothes and so on, that there the benefit comes at
the expense of some wear and tear and therefore the מעילה me'ila
requires to transgress the הנאה, hana'ah, the benefit has to be accompanied
with that פגם, pegam, wear and tear. So the by the case
by the סוטה sota they're making the comparison that that is a
sort of benefit without a פגם. pegam.
And why did they say סוטה sota and not אשת איש? eishet
ish? סוטה Sota might be the innocent.
It's true, because you only have the פסוק pasuk of כי תמעול
מעל ki tim'ol ma'al by that case.
Right, but it fits more with
it does the way the תורה Torah describes it, איש איש כי
תשטה אשתו ומעלה בו מעל ושכב איש אותה שכבת זרע, ish ish
ki tisteh ishto umala vo ma'al veshachav ish ota shichvat zera, the
תורה Torah starts by describing as if the adultery had already occurred,
and then it sort of shifts to say that the husband is
is is suspicious of that scenario. But it starts by describing that
scenario, right? It says איש איש כי תשטה אשתו ומעלה בו מעל
ושכב איש אותה שכבת זרע ish ish ki tisteh ishto umala vo
ma'al veshachav ish ota shichvat zera and right and then it says
and he doesn't know. I understand. So you're right, it really means
the פרשה parsha of סוטה sota but it's describing the act of
adultery.
But can you do a סוטה sota on an ארוסה? arusa?
What?
No, right?
Otherwise it would be like literally פגם, pegam, like in in
like yeah, you're exactly true. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara so okay,
so that's you're right. So it's the פרשה parsha of סוטה sota
but it is the act of adultery. Okay, so that's what we
learn from there, that it's that הנאה hana'ah by itself is an
act of מעילה. me'ila. גבי הקדש נמי. Gabei hekdesh nami.
So therefore we apply that to הקדש. hekdesh. נתן טבעת בידה, Natan
taba'at beyada, wearing a ring, מעלה, ma'ala, it's a מעילה me'ila even
though there is no loss to הקדש, hekdesh, but it's taking benefit
that does not belong to you. כי אקיש רחמנא לעבודה זרה, Ki
akish rachmana l'avoda zara, now what do we learn from עבודה זרה?
avoda zara? דעד דאיכא שינוי, De'ad de'ika shinui,
until there is some change, and here change means, as the way
תוספות Tosafot understands, change of רשות, reshus, like taking possession, removing away
from God and putting under yourself under the control of עבודה זרה.
avoda zara. So taking the object away from הקדש hekdesh and taking
it into your control. That's a different form of מעילה, me'ila, not
about benefit, but about taking away and taking possession. Okay, so גבי...
so what would be the case? גבי הקדש hekdesh, נמי עד דביקא
בקורדום.
ויפחת ופגום, Veyifchat ufagum, they take out those words again. The text
is a little problematic. So it says until you basically chop with
the hatchet. Now that's a little funny because normally we would have
assumed that the chopping with the hatchet is a case of deriving
benefit. Here's this hatchet, I chop with it, I chop some wood,
I derive benefit, and it's just like the other case. Maybe I
derived benefit with some type of a פגם, pegam, and maybe that's
a way to read this here, if you keep the words ויפחת
ופגום, veyifchat ufagum, which means okay, so there's times where it's about
deriving benefit and coming after some type of a loss to the
object itself.
We're talking about the hatchet of הקדש, hekdesh. is that what you're
talking about? Yeah, the hatchet of הקדש.
Hekdesh So therefore if I cut the wood, it sort of weakens
the hatchet a little bit? Yeah, right. Of course there's wear and
tear on a hatchet when you chop with it. Okay, so now
learning it that way, which would be more the straight the text
we have, would not be תוספות's Tosafot way. תוספות Tosafot wants to
say that the עבודה זרה avoda zara comparison is about just the
physical taking of possession. But reading the text we have it could
be a sense of deriving benefit and causing some loss. Of course
then the analogy to עבודה זרה avoda zara is strange. Where's the
benefit? Where's the loss? What is it? That you're giving now קרבנות
korbanos to the בעל Ba'al and you're not giving קרבנות korbanos to
the... How do you... is that what
the... Tosfos takes out the word and others take out the word
ופגמו פגום, u-pagemu pagum, the pgam is not as relevant here, the
loss, and it's basically saying the case of the hatchet is a
case of taking possession. But as I've said, but why does it
mention chopping with the hatchet? Because as I've said and we're going
to see in the next Mishna, it's not so obvious how you
do an act of stealing from Hekdesh. Right, I mean if it's
sort of in Temple treasury and you sneak into the treasury and
you take it and you run away, okay, that's stealing. But like
if I take, let's say I have my hatchet and I say
I maktish this to Beis Ha-Mikdash and now it belongs to Hekdesh,
and now I pick it up and I take it to the
other room, right? Have I stolen it from Hekdesh? When does it,
how do you define that act of stealing? So that might be
that if I actually go ahead and use it for myself, of
course that's showing that I am possessing it. Of course why that's
not also an act of Hana'ah is a good question as well.
But that's always a little tricky to define what is that act
of stealing from Hekdesh. But anyway, that's how Tosfos wants to learn
this. So what we learn from Sotah is deriving benefit. What we
learn from the hatchet is either benefit with pgam or it's not
that, what we learn from Avodah Zarah and apply to the hatchet
case is either benefit with pgam or more simply, you know conceptually,
the idea of taking possession, taking away and taking possession. And what
did we learn from Terumah? And akishe Rachmana l'Terumah, it's linked to
Terumah. Mah Terumah ki yochal prat l'mazik. By Terumah we darshen the
pasuk of somebody eats from Terumah they pay back the Kohen, but
if they just damage the Terumah that is not the obligations there.
Now again, the question is you might have to pay because of
mazik, although Terumah's a little funny because it's sort of mammon she'ein
lo tovin, who exactly owns Terumah? But anyway, the act of willful
destruction is not included in that parsha. So gabe Hekdesh nami kol
davar, not davar, kol davar achilah. Anything that is edible, ki mazik
lei patur, if you damage it you're exempt. Now Rashi and Tosfos
jump in to say it's not limited to anything edible, it means
that by Hekdesh it is not Me'ilah when you damage. When you
damage that's a separate
conversation, damaging Hekdesh, okay, destroying Hekdesh, but it's not Me'ilah. Me'ilah is
very much not you know taking diverting and you're taking possession, you're
getting Hana'ah. The pgam might be a requirement of the Hana'ah but
the focus is you got possession, you got the benefit, you got
it under your possession. So from those three models we learn those
ideas. Number one, that there's a form of Hana'ah by itself when
things aren't accompanied with benefit.
Number two, when things don't normally are...
I mean aren't normally accompanied with a loss. Number two, there's an
idea of Me'ilah as stealing and taking possession and all these are
sort of you taking for yourself and diverting from Hekdesh in particular
ways. And the third is when things normally do accompany a loss
and this is what we also learn from Terumah, like eating, a
loss comes with the benefiting, then it's only Me'ilah when that loss
accompanies. Okay, but straight causing a loss to Hekdesh, destroying, that's not
Me'ilah. Me'ilah is basically you taking something, benefit or ownership for yourself,
okay, and that's Me'ilah.
So can let me ask a question on that? Yeah. Again my
tomato case, it became wormy right and then I started to eat
it. Does that consider Me'ilah or is it considered not bar achilah
or
it depends, I mean if the thing is still worth a shveh
prutah, I mean if it's like what you're saying, let's say it's
Hana'ah shelo kedarkah, would that be Hana'ah by
Hekdesh? Not sure. Depends partly what pasuk we learn it from, what
pasuk we learn the issur Me'ilah from. Rambam learns issur Me'ilah from
pasuk of ki yochal of lo sochlu. Anyway, so that's one question,
Hana'ah shelo kedarkah. And the other question is, is it a shveh
prutah or not? Does it consider Hana'ah shveh prutah eating the wormy
flour? But yeah, that would those be those issues.
Yeah, so there's the conclusion that it's either or benefit or taking
away?
Yes, so no, both, there are those two models. Now conceptually, what
do we do to link those models? You could say that those
are separate tracks, but we know not that way because we know
for example that you can combine different types of Me'ilah. So if
I steal a half of prutah and I anoint you with a
half of prutah or me with a half of prutah, those are
both those combine right? Or I wear I wear a Me'ilah ring
which gives me a half of a prutah of benefit and I
steal a half of prutah. So if you can combine they're clearly
not completely separate tracks, right?
Can one on its own be considered?
Oh sure, totally, right.
But I'm making a further point, not only are both of those
tracks ways of Me'ilah, but you have to define them in some
unified way because you can actually do a half of each and
it's considered an act of Me'ilah. Okay, so the basic question is
becomes, you know, the way normally it's conceptualized by the Achroneim is
do you define it all as a type of stealing? But
you can
steal... Or do you define it as a type of, it's about
deriving benefit. You can derive benefit by wearing something, by using something,
or you can derive benefit by adding it to your possessions. You
know, so they try to find some unifying theme of those two,
but they do seem to be two tracks, but there's a need
to bring them together in one in a conceptual way.
But that depends what it is, no? Meaning if it's jewelry, and
it's worn, okay, then I get benefit by wearing it. But let's
say it's a תרומה Terumah I put in my display case, and
I was like, oh, what a nice piece of תרומה, Terumah, I'm
not getting any benefit from that.
Okay, so
then you don't get benefit and you didn't steal it, it's not
תרומה. Terumah. But that's not my point. My point was that our
two tracks, either one by itself is מעילה Me'ilah and even a
half of each is מעילה, Me'ilah, you know, a half of a
פרוטה Perutah each, and that forces you to create some conceptual unifying
definition. Let's keep on going in the גמרא. Gemara. כיצד נתנן כבולות,
Keitzad natnan kavolot, so now it deals with the משנה, Mishnah, which
says what's a form of benefit by something that does not normally
accompany loss? That would be for example wearing a golden necklace. Okay,
so there's no loss and therefore the benefit alone is an act
of מעילה. Me'ilah. אמר ליה רב כהנא לרב זביד, Amar lei Rav
Kahana le-Rav Zvid, so רב כהנא Rav Kahana said to רב זביד:
Rav Zvid: ודהבא לאו בר אפקומי הוא? Ve-dahava lav bar ifkumei hu?
Are you telling me that gold does not suffer loss over time?
והא דהבא דכלתי דנון, Ve-ha-dahava de-khaltei de-Nun, so it's interesting they're using
a very specific, a very real world example. How about the daughter-in-law
of this guy נון? Nun? He gave them a lot of gold
or whatever, והיכא אזיל, ve-heicha azil, and you know where did it
disappear to? I don't know, maybe he used it to pay gambling
debts or something. But anyway, but apparently it means that somehow the
jewelry got worn away and it's not what it used to be.
So you see that the stuff does suffer a loss over time.
So אמר ליה, amar lei, he said back then, דלמא דהבא דרמיא
אכלסיה, Dilma de-hava de-ramya a-khalsaiya,
again, I'm just explaining the way the מפורש meforash here in תוספות
Tosafos explain it, there might be some other translation of this or
meaning of this. Maybe it's like the gold that your daughter-in-law's just
throw all around the place. What? Which apparently means that okay, if
you leave it exposed to the elements it will, you know, suffer
some loss, but under normal circumstances, you know, if you treat it
properly and then, you know, using a gold jewelry does not incur
some loss to the object itself. Okay, so that's the way that,
that's their explain of the debate. Ah, doesn't it happen? Sometime, yeah,
if you don't treat it right. But normally it won't happen. ועוד
נהי דלא איתחזיא פגימה לאלתר, Ve-od nehi de-lo it-hazya pegima le-alter, it
said, and here's really a more important halakhic point.
It's true all we're saying is that the loss does not occur
at the time of the benefit. לעולם מי לא איתהוי פגימה? Le-olam
mi lo ithavei pegima? We're not saying that there's never any loss
that occurs to the object, but we're saying that in the, you
know, few seconds that you wear it, the few minutes that you
wear it, the object did not depreciate in value. It might depreciate
in value over 20
years, okay, but over the time that you used it there was
no depreciation in value and that's necessary to define, and in order
to say that there's a requirement that there be some loss is
only by things that are normally accompanied with a depreciation of value.
Not things that depreciate sometime, but things that normally in their usage,
you know, within a relative, within a defined period of usage is
accompanied with depreciation. And for those types of things it's not מעילה
Me'ilah until you actually until a depreciation happens.
But we don't say that by the shirt. Let's say I take
the shirt for an hour, right? You say לא נפגם, lo nifgam,
no,
so the assumption is that they actually it is, that once it
gets every time it gets worn it gets worth a little bit
less. You know, that's the assumption. Now you might say that, you
know, people aren't going to be saying it's now worth 10.98 and
now that you wore it again it's worth 10.96 and 10.94, but
that's the assumption. The assumption is that it actually does get worth
a little bit less each time, whereas here it's so microscopic, you
know, the any possible depreciation that it's not considered to have occurred.
That seems to be the difference. Okay, whereas there what?
That's not a nice exchange they had, each one talked about the
other's daughter-in-law, right? Their daughters, but their daughters-in-law, it's in a very
negative- Right,
because they were all sort of putting down other daughters.
Why are they watching what their daughter-in-law is doing with their jewelry?
I mean, these are Rabbis, what?
What else is going on? What are they doing looking at their
daughters-in-law?
Yeah, boy! That's רב כהנא Rav Kahana and רב זביד,
Rav
Zvid,
they're major Rabbis, they're so interested in their daughters-in-law's jewelry and how
they're handling their jewelry.
Right. Of course, you know, sometimes people complain that the Rabbis are
always building castles in the air and they're not looking at like
real facts on the ground.
So here's where they choose to look at the
facts.
Exactly! Ground-level facts. Right. Focusing. Okay, yeah, I would have been surp-
I would
have been surp- So Gemara says הנאה מן החטאת. Hana'ah min hachattas.
Okay, so now the last case of the משנה. Mishnah. All right,
all right, point's made, point is taken. הנאה מן החטאת. Hana'ah min
hachattas.
What do you, what do you want me to do? All right,
הנאה מן החטאת. Hana'ah min hachattas. All right, so now, so now
the משנה Mishnah said the following: if you derive benefit, now this
is an interesting משנה, Mishnah, if you derive benefit from a live
חטאת, chataas, then it doesn't require, then even with, then only if
it is accompanied with פגם. pegam. You could imagine that. You ride
the animal, it makes the animal worth a little bit less, it
causes some depreciation in the animal. But there could be a case
where you get benefit without causing any loss. It's a sheep and
you, I don't know, you warm yourself in the wool that's on
the sheep itself or something like that. So there's no loss to
the object. Okay, but anyway the משנה Mishnah says when it's a
live חטאת chataas there has to be loss because normally when you
derive benefit from live animals there's a loss, so it has to
accompany loss. When it's dead, even without loss and I'll discuss dead
in a minute, but first let's focus on the גמרא Gemara about
the live. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, הנאה מן החטאת.
Hana'ah min hachattas. The גמרא Gemara says נחזי, Nichze, let's take a
look. אי בבהמה תמימה, Ei bi'beheimah temimah, if the animal is unblemished,
היינו כוס של זהב, Hainu kos shel zahav, that's a golden cup.
Now what does that mean? Golden cup is the paradigm of the
case where benefit without loss. Now what do you mean though? Who
cares whether it's unblemished? There's still the physical reality that when somebody
normally uses an animal there comes some depreciation in the animal itself.
What difference does it make that it's תמים, tamim, meaning able to
be used as a קרבן, korban, why should that change the reality
of whether loss normally is part of the equation or not? So
the way everybody explains this is the following, and this is very
important because it gets to the question about conceptually what מעילה me'ilah
is. They say it's true the animal is worth less if I
use it whether it's תמים tamim or בעל מום. ba'al mum. But
הקדש Hekdesh. doesn't suffer a loss because if it's going to be
a קרבן, korban, right, then whether it's a קרבן korban worth a
thousand dollars or nine hundred and ninety-nine dollars, there's no loss to
הקדש. Hekdesh The מזבח mizbeach still gets its קרבן. korban. Although the
ראב"ד Ravad says, well, I don't know, I mean maybe the כהנים,
Kohanim, the leather is somewhat impacted or whatever, but anyway fundamentally the
מזבח mizbeach still gets its קרבן. korban. Okay. If however it is,
as the גמרא Gemara is going to say, let's read the answer.
So
אמר רב פפא בבעלת מום עסקינן. Amar Rav Papa bi'ba'alas mum askinan.
It has a blemish. What does that mean? So if it has
a blemish what do you do with an animal with a blemish?
You redeem it. Right. And therefore if you redeem it, you're going
to translate it into cash because you sell it for the value
and so on. And therefore there is an implication of that loss
because instead of selling it for a thousand dollars, you're now going
to sell it for nine hundred and ninety-nine. So now that is
very important because that says the idea of loss is not just
the physical reality is one that this use accompanies loss, but it's
that it's the type of a thing actually normally loss would occur
to the מקדש, Mikdash, to, you know, God, to the temple, and
only then is it required if that's a normal part that loss
is accompanied. But when it's not relevant, not. But I will point
out that this is tricky for the following reason: even if it's
a קרבן korban with a מום, mum, in the end where's that
money going to go?
What do you do when you redeem a קרבן korban with a
מום? mum? But what use? You have to buy another קרבן korban
with it. Right. Which gets back to the point that it's just
going to the מזבח. mizbeach. So it's not really that in the
end of the day הקדש Hekdesh is going to lose out something
in its bank account. It's still just going to be a קרבן
korban at the end of it. But it's that in one case,
so it's not even that question of will הקדש hekdesh lose out,
it's more like how do we even think of it? In one
case we think of it, we look at it and we see
dollar signs. Okay, it's true those dollar signs are going to go
to the מזבח, mizbeach, but we see dollar signs. So therefore when
we can talk about the idea, oh my god, the dollar amount
is going down, and that's sort of conceptualized as a loss. If
we look at it and we don't see dollar signs, this is
just going to be used whatever its value is, okay, then we
don't see what happened as a loss because that's not how we
conceptualize. So it's not even so much the reality of a loss
as it's more like whether it's conceived of as a loss and
the role that that plays. So that's pretty important, this question here
about conceptualizing about the issue of loss, which would actually mean that
any should mean the logic derivation is this, that anything that's a
כלי שרת, kli shares, anything that is an object used in the
בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash like a golden vessel or whatever, all of
those types of things loss is irrelevant. It's all about the הנאה,
hana'ah, it's not about the loss because we always just focus on
the thing and we're using the thing and not on its value.
That would seem to be the case, but it's possible to distinguish.
Okay. So that is the issue of the live חטאת. chataas. Now
the משנה Mishnah ends by saying a dead חטאת chataas also, it's
the הנאה hana'ah alone without a loss. Why is that true? When
I normally use dead animals, for whatever dog food or something, there's
a loss. So why if it's a dead חטאת chatas even without
a loss? So here it's the same point, because it's true if
in the normal world, if you used a dead animal, it would
be accompanied with a loss to the object itself. But as far
as הקדש hekdesh is concerned, a dead קרבן korban has absolutely no
value. And therefore, there is a concept of הקדש hekdesh losing something
is not relevant, and therefore it's all about the benefit. So what
you see by the combination of these cases is within this discussion
that sometimes מעילה me'ilah requires a loss, it's not only the idea
that a loss in the normal world normally accompanies the use of
the object, but it's also the idea that conceptually הקדש hekdesh is
losing. If there's no concept of הקדש hekdesh losing, then there can't
be a point of saying that a loss is required.
Yes. We say that for a מום mum in חטאת chatas when
it's alive לא מעל עד שיפגום, lo mo'al ad sheyifgom, so that
can
be
like a temporary loss, right? Let's say like אינה, ayenah, it could
be for like a day, and then the next day it's okay,
right? So then even if הקדש hekdesh isn't losing on anything...
it is losing right now, for what you tell her right now,
it would be worth less.
Right, it doesn't have to be long-term, correct. But then even with
the
בעל מום... ba'al mum... it's the same idea, right? I mean even
though a בעל מום ba'al mum will go to the as a
קרבן korban and you can wait, I mean not a קרבן, korban,
go sell him through the קרבן korban process... but you see dollar
signs, and even so right now it's a temporary loss, even though
tomorrow, right... yep, correct.
Okay, now let's look at the next משנה. mishnah. The next משנה
mishnah actually teaches what we learned yesterday from a ברייתא, braisa, but
here it is being taught in the משנה. mishnah. So let's take
a look. Actually it wasn't fully spelled out in the ברייתא. braisa.
So now the top of יט עמוד ב. yud tes amud beis.
נהנה כחצי פרוטה פגם כחצי פרוטה. neheneh k'chezi prutah, pagam k'chezi prutah.
Let's say you derived benefit of a half of a פרוטה prutah
and you caused a half of a פרוטה prutah of loss, right?
That's obviously not going to be מעילה. me'ilah. מעילה me'ilah requires a
full פרוטה's prutah worth of benefit. Or שנהנה בשווה פרוטה, she-neheneh bishveh
prutah,
you got a הנאה hana'ah a benefit of a פרוטה prutah from
this object you used, בדבר אחד ופגם בשווה פרוטה בדבר אחר. bidavar
echad upagam bishveh prutah bidavar acher. And the loss occurred to another
object. So somehow, you could just be talking about two separate acts.
I was drinking from this golden cup, well that actually doesn't require
it, but whatever, I was doing, I was wearing some type of
a garment
and I was at the same time I was damaging some other
item with my other hand, some type of a thing that there
obviously there could be more interesting cases which I just couldn't think
of in where actually they're related acts but nevertheless it's not occurring
in the same object. And that's the point. The benefit you get
has to be a פרוטה prutah and it has to cause a
loss in the same object that you are deriving the benefit from.
Both have to be a פרוטה's prutah worth. Well that we're going
to talk about in a minute. Okay. לא מעל, lo ma'al, you
didn't, you weren't מועל... mo'el... עד שיהא נהנה בשווה פרוטה ויפגום בשווה
פרוטה בדבר אחד, ad sheyeheh neheneh bishveh prutah v'yifgom bishveh prutah bidavar
echad, until you derive benefit of a פרוטה prutah and the simplest
way to read this is you cause a loss of a פרוטה
prutah in the same object. Now this seems to say that the
actual and this is the first time we're seeing it, the actual
damage has to be a פרוטה's prutah worth of damage. Now that
I would have to tell you is a little bit troubling from
two perspectives. Number one is that conceptually מעילה me'ilah is not about
loss, conceptually you can have הנאה hana'ah by itself, right? We said
it's like the golden cup. If you just damage it it's not
מעילה. me'ilah. Conceptually מעילה me'ilah is about benefit. Sometimes to define it
as really taking the benefit it has to come with some loss
of the object, but you would not normally assume that that means
that there has to be a loss worth of a פרוטה prutah
unless you just say that there's no way to measure the loss
if it's less than a פרוטה. prutah. But that's one point. Number
one. Number two is that most of these cases it's hard to
imagine that that's really true. I mean we have cases where I
take a hammer and I bang a hammer, right? Or I put
on a shirt or all these types of cases. Are all these
cases that there's exactly that there's a פרוטה's prutah loss? I mean
first of all it would be not a too much valuable, it
would be a weird object that the amount of benefit you got
was always exactly equivalent to the depreciation of it. But I guess
it's... but that doesn't have to be normally they're just disproportionate, but
minimally you need a פרוטה prutah from each. Okay so that is
definitely the simple way of reading it but conceptually I find that
hard and practically I can imagine that some of the scenarios that
we discuss of מעילה me'ilah don't always accompany a פרוטה prutah of
damage. So I'm wondering if it's possible to read this, and I'm
just putting it out as a possibility, that there's a question here
by the way of the גרסא girsa of this משנה. mishnah. We
have a ב beis in both of these words, עד שיהנה בשווה
פרוטה ויפגום בשווה פרוטה. ad sheyeheneh bishveh prutah v'yifgom bishveh prutah.
But there are a lot of other גרסאות girsos of the משנה
mishnah that have the גרסא girsa the following way. עד שיהנה שווה
פרוטה ויפגום בשווה פרוטה, ad sheyeheneh sheveh prutah v'yifgom bishveh prutah,
that there's only a ב beis in the second phrase. And what
that could mean is your הנאה hana'ah has to be a פרוטה's
prutah worth of הנאה hana'ah and you cause פגם pegam in that
thing that you are. that deriving the benefit from the bet means
like in that שוה פרוטה, shvei perutah, not of a value of
a שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. Anyway, that may be a stretch, but
I just put it out there because I do admit the simple
sense here is that it has to be a פרוטה's perutah worth
of פגם pegam and maybe that says that halakhically less than that
we can't measure, we can't say it really occurred. So it has
to be that. But again I just find that difficult A, that
that's true in all these scenarios, and B, conceptually פגם pegam is
not really the important thing, the important thing is the הנאה. hana'ah.
But the simple sense is you do need a פרוטה perutah of
each. Yes.
So let me ask you a question on that. So let's say,
you know, I'm just making this up. Let's say a פרוטה perutah
is a dollar, right? Yep.
A פרוטה's perutah more like 5 cents.
No, no I understand.
But let's say 5 cents so we have a right sense of
it.
Okay. But then, and you know, and you bought this at like,
you know, some second hand thrift shop and donated to הקדש hekdesh
for 4 cents. So I can wear it a whole day and
destroy it and not be over anything because it wasn't a שוה
פרוטה? shvei perutah?
Again, yes. If you get הנאה hana'ah less than a פרוטה, perutah,
it's the same type of
thing if it wasn't פגום בשוה פרוטה, pgum bishvei perutah, was never
a שוה פרוטה shvei perutah to begin with. Right. So I can
just utterly destroy the thing, right?
Right. Yeah and it wouldn't be מעילה. me'ilah. It doesn't mean it's
מותר mutar but it wouldn't be מעילה. me'ilah. Right. Okay. So then
right. So let's take a look now. So that's anyway, the גמרא's
Gemara not going to discuss that because that was, that basic concept
of הנאה hana'ah and פגם pegam was discussed on the earlier דף.
daf. So now
we go on though to a new idea, which the
גמרא Gemara will discuss. אין מועל אחר מועל במוקדשין אלא בבהמה וכלי
שרת בלבד. ein mo'el achar mo'el b'mukdashin ela b'behema v'khli shareis bilvad.
You can never do מעילה me'ilah twice in the same object. What's
that famous Buddhist saying, whatever, you can't cross the same river twice.
No? Does nobody know that? Okay, anyway, because once you cross it,
it's not the same river. Okay, anyway, so אין מועל אחר מועל
במוקדשין, ein mo'el achar mo'el b'mukdashin, so you can never be מועל
mo'el in the same object
twice, אלא בבהמה וכלי שרת בלבד. ela b'behema v'khli shareis bilvad. Except
if it's a קרבן korban or כלי שרת. kli shareis. Why? Because
now we are going to be introduced to a new concept of
מעילה. me'ilah. And a new concept of מעילה me'ilah is, as soon
as you are מועל mo'el in the object, the object
becomes, well, de-sanctified. It lose its, it loses קדושה. kedusha. And that
you can understand if the idea of מעילה me'ilah some sense of
trespass, a violation, of diverting, right? Then that sense that it's now
been taken away means that its קדושה, kedusha, you know, has been
has been injured and therefore it disappears. So if I basically take
this, you know, הקדש hekdesh. shirt and I wear it and I
get some הנאה hana'ah from it or, then, then it stops being
הקדש. hekdesh, So the next person or the next time I wear
it, I won't do מעילה. me'ilah. It might still be owned by
הקדש, hekdesh. you know that's a different question, but it doesn't have
intrinsic קדושה kedusha and I now, you cannot be מועל mo'el twice.
But with the exception of a קרבן korban and כלי שרת. kli
shareis. Why is a קרבן korban and כלי שרת kli shareis different?
Because קרבן korban and כלי שרת kli shareis are קדושת הגוף, kedushas
haguf, right? Are intrinsic קדושה. kedusha. It's not just about ownership. Other
things it's about ownership. So it's about ownership and now, by the
way,
the sense of קדושה kedusha identity of the object is קדוש, kadosh,
is much less when fundamentally the קדושה's kedusha about ownership. Things that
are owned are, the normal thing you would do with them is
sell them and get the proceeds, right? It's very natural for them
to go out of the control of הקדש.
hekdesh But not a כלי שרת kli shareis then.
That's why. Other than כלי שרת. kli shareis. But if it's just
about בדק הבית bedek habayis and ownership, not about קדושת הגוף. kedushas
haguf. So therefore there once the קדושה kedusha is sort of violated,
it leaves because the קדושה kedusha anyway was not so much about
the the fundamental identity of the object. Okay, and it normally could
have easily been taken away anyway. So whereas so whereas by the
whole idea of בהמה behema and כלי שרת kli shareis where the
קדושה kedusha is very much about the identity, where it does not
you cannot normally redeem a בהמה behema unless it has a מום.
mum. כלי שרת kli shareis presumably as well. I'll talk about that.
So those types of things, it's really fully identified that way. So
then it is, you know, then it's much harder to to change
that identity. Okay, so it talks, you know, you could think about
the you could think about turning that into a מוסר שמוז, mussar
shmooze, right? It's one thing if you have an affiliation. So things
happen you could drop the affiliation. But if it actually becomes your
identity and how you identify yourself, you know then you hold on
to that even when things happen to to challenge it. So that
anyway the point about the בהמה behema and the כלי שרת. kli
shareis. כיצד, keitzad, what's the example? רכב אגבי בהמה, rachav agabei behema,
you rode on an animal, ובא חבירו ורכב, uva chaveiro v'rachav, and
somebody else came and rode on it, ובא חבירו ורכב, uva chaveiro
v'rachav, and somebody else
came, assuming this is a קרבן, korban, כולן מעלו, kulan ma'alu, they
all were מועל. mo'el. שתה בכוס של זהב, shasa b'khos shel zahav,
again assuming it's a כלי שרת kli shareis used in the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, you drank, ובא חבירו ושתה, uva chaveiro v'shasa, ובא
חבירו ושתה, uva chaveiro v'shasa, כולן מעלו, kulan ma'alu,
they all did מעילה. me'ilah. תלש מן החטאת, talash min hachatas, ובא
חבירו ותלש, uva chaveiro v'talash,
now we're saying explicitly חטאת, chatas, interesting why we didn't say it
before. Maybe because a חטאת chatas is normally a sheep, so you're
not going to Riding, but it's a you'll pull the wool. You
pulled wool from the חטאת chatas and somebody else came and did
it, ובא חברו ותלש, u'va chaveiro ve'talash, and somebody else came and
did it, כולם מעלו, kulam ma'alu, they all did מעילה me'ila again
because it is a קרבן, korban, so therefore the קדושה kedusha does
not go away. רבי אומר, Rabbi omer, כל דבר שאין לו פדיון,
kol davar she'ein lo pidyon, or some have the גירסא, girsa, כל
דבר שאין לו... what was the other גירסא girsa here? Not
פדיון, pidyon, but פגם. pagam. Okay, but I'm going to read פדיון,
pidyon, it makes it easier because פגם pagam introduces gets us back
into that other discussion. יש מעילה אחר מעילה. yeish me'ila achar me'ila.
Rather than calling it בהמה וכלי שרת, beheima u'klei shares, he calls
it something that doesn't have פדיון, pidyon, which seems to be the
same point. Normal things that are just owned by הקדש hekdesh. have
פדיון, pidyon, could be redeemed, meaning could be sold and the קדושה
kedusha removed. But בהמה וכלי שרת beheima u'klei shares one minute, a
בהמה beheima unless it has a מום, mum, but if it doesn't
have a מום, mum, right, then these things, they retain their identity,
they're not transferred out of הקדש. hekdesh, And because they're not normally
transferred out of הקדש, hekdesh also when the הקדש hekdesh. is somehow
violated, the קדושה kedusha does still remain. So the גמרא Gemara is
going to ask how's that different than the first statement, but it
seems to be more or less the first statement.
So this would also seem to potentially exclude birds.
Oh, that's a good point. Birds no, you mean birds no, birds
don't have פדיון. pidyon.
That's exactly right.
No, but he's saying don't have פדיון, pidyon, but the birds are
just like a קרבן. korban. Meaning a bird with that's let's say
מחוסר אבר mechussar eiver meaning if a קרבן korban has a מום,
mum, then it would have מעילה אחר מעילה me'ila achar me'ila the
other way. A bird, even when it's missing a limb and can't
be brought as a קרבן, korban, would still have מעילה אחר מעילה
me'ila achar me'ila because you can't redeem it. Right? That would probably
be that would be correct. I do also want to say that
as if we're not confused enough, but you know, again, thinking about
the two tracks of מעילה me'ila הנאה hana'ah and stealing, right, you
would logically say that this idea that the קדושה kedusha can go
away after מעילה me'ila makes a lot more sense if we're talking
about a concept of stealing הקדש. hekdesh. Right? Then it's about I'm
taking possession of הקדש. hekdesh And then if it's the type of
thing that normally is like that the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash normally
sells and is very much about possession, right, the types of just
things that they own, there you could say that the קדושה kedusha
goes away. If it's just about deriving benefit, then why the קדושה
kedusha goes away is not so obvious. Nevertheless, the משנה mishna makes
it clear, right, that it deals with both cases. It deals with
riding on the animal, drinking the cup, and pulling the wool, which
is more like the stealing because you're not deriving benefit at this
moment, you're just taking it. So it sort of seems that even
in the case of benefit, that violates the קדושה kedusha and the
קדושה kedusha will go away unless it's בהמה וכלי שרת. beheima u'klei
shares. Although I could have distinguished, and I mentioned this because תוספות
Tosafos quotes a תוספתא Tosefta that actually seems to make that distinction.
That actually seems to say that even when it's not a כלי
שרת, kli shares, if it's only the type of מעילה me'ila of
benefit, that never affects the קדושה. kedusha. And the only thing do
you
mean like over the shirt?
Like taking a hammer and taking right, taking a hammer and chopping
wood with it or whatever, you know, a הקדש and chopping wood
with it, that never the only type of מעילה me'ila that the
תוספתא Tosefta seems to say that can cause the קדושה kedusha to
go away is if it's the מעילה me'ila of taking possession, which
makes a lot of sense, I think. Nevertheless, our משנה mishna doesn't
distinguish. Our משנה mishna seems to say that any type of מעילה
me'ila makes the קדושה kedusha go away unless it is these things
of like a קרבן korban or כלי שרת kli shares where the
קדושה kedusha is very much about its identity. And then it does
not go away.
Right, so according to the תוספתא, Tosefta, if I take the shirt
and I wear it, then the shirt is always קדוש. kadosh. Yes.
And then
unless you actually tried to steal the shirt. If you just used
it, that would not that's what the תוספתא Tosefta says.
If you steal it, why does the קדושה kedusha if you own
something and someone steals it, it's still yours.
Right, but we're still dealing with this idea it's correct that you
have violated and impinged, but I but I but there if the
whole nature of the קדושה kedusha is about ownership, and I am
now bringing my ownership directly to contest it, or you know, directly
to challenge it, then that is a much greater sort of violation
and a much greater at least attempt to push out its קדושה
kedusha identity, I think. And therefore maybe that's the case where you're
right, in naturally just because I take your thing it doesn't become
mine, but I will say when you learn בבא קמא, Bava Kamma,
I do get certain rights to it just by the fact of
my physical possession, even if it's something that I stole. It's called
קנייני גניבה kinyanei gneiva or קנייני גזילה. kinyanei gezeila. So there there
is a greater sense, I think, of it pushing the other the
other status away than the הנאה hana'ah is. But anyway, that is
I agree that in the normal secular context it would not be
fully. So there's certainly a חידוש chiddush here. The תוספתא Tosefta disagrees
with the משנה. mishna. Okay, anyway back to the גמרא. Gemara. I'm
just sharing it because I found that interesting. But anyway for us,
the point is all types of מעילה me'ila cause the קדושה kedusha
to go away unless it's by a בהמה וכלי שרת. beheima u'klei
shares. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאן מתניתין? Man masnisin? Who's
our משנה? mishna? רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemia היא. hi. It is Rebbi
Nechemia. דתניא, De'tanya, אין מעילה אחר מעילה ein me'ila achar me'ila אלא
בבהמה בלבד. ela be'beheima bilvad. So this ברייתא braisa says only by
קרבנות. korbanos. רבי נחמיה Rebbi Nechemia אומר omer, בהמה וכלי שרת. beheima
u'klei shares. בהמה וכלי שרת. beheima u'klei shares. So that's our משנה
mishna כלי שרת. kli shares. So what's the issue about the כלי
שרת? kli shares? So מאי טעמא דתנא קמא? mai ta'ama de'Tanna Kamma?
What's the reason of the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that limited it
to בהמה? beheima?
קסבר בעניינא דבהמה כתיב. kasavar b'inyana d'behemah k'tiv. The whole idea of
מעילה me'ilah and where we get presumably the concept that things retain
their קדושה kedusha after מעילה, me'ilah, it's interesting. I would have said
tell me the חידוש chiddush that it loses its קדושה, kedusha, but
anyway where we get the idea that it retains its קדושה kedusha
is around animals. How do you know? דכתיב De'chtiv באיל האשם. b'eil
ha'asham. It says that the כהן kohen will atone for this person
with the ram of the אשם. asham. That's what it says by
מעילה. me'ilah. And that's redundant because we know it's the ram of
the אשם. asham. Why does it repeat? So the דרשה drasha is
this ram, any ram will retain its identity as an אשם asham
no matter how many times מעילה me'ilah is done to it. I
mean you understand the פסוק pasuk is talking about the קרבן korban
you're bringing to atone for the מעילה, me'ilah, but the דרשה drasha
is using it as a paradigm, as a model for a thing
you could do מעילה me'ilah to. And something will always be an
אשם asham no matter how many times. So he says, we learn
this concept that it retains its identity from בהמה, behemah, from קרבן.
korban. I'm going to limit it to that. רבי נחמיה אמר לך,
Rebbe Nechemya amar lach, רבי נחמיה Rebbe Nechemya could say to you,
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, I can figure out כלי שרת, chlei sharet,
I don't need the פסוק. pasuk. I can figure it out from
a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. What's the קל וחומר? kal v'chomer? אם
אחרים מביא לקדושתן, im acherim mevi l'kedushatan, the כלי שרת chlei sharet
has the ability to sanctify what's in it. So when you put
for example water in a כלי שרת, chlei sharet, if you're going
to use it for the water libation on סוכות Succos on the
מזבח, mizbeach, or oil or whatever, that gives the water or the
oil קדושת הגוף. kedushat haguf. So being in the כלי שרת chlei
sharet transfers, instills קדושה kedusha into the object. If it can do
that, הוא עצמו לא כל שכן, hu atzmo lo kol sheken, how
much more so should it have the power to retain its own
קדושה? kedusha? If it has the power to, you know, to bestow
קדושה, kedusha, it should certainly have the power to retain its own
even when it is violated. That's the קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. One
second, I want to point out that תוספות Tosafot says, makes a
point, which is a very fascinating question, which is,
can you, is there פדיון pidyon by כלי שרת? chlei sharet? If
you decide you want to de- what's that word again for museums
when they sell their- deaccession?
I think is what- like there's some fancy word that means that
they just really want to sell it but they want to make
it sound like they're not just getting rid of it. So anyway,
if you want to do that to your כלי שרת, chlei sharet,
can you do it? Is there a concept that it needs מום,
mum, that it has to become unusable? Can you just, if you
want or the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash wants to, can the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash just sell it? So תוספות Tosafot says he doesn't
want to accept that the distinction here between a קרבן korban and
כלי שרת chlei sharet is arbitrary. Oh, it's a פסוק. pasuk. Who
cares? I mean there's got to be some reason. So תוספות Tosafot
actually argues that certainly according to the first opinion, כלי שרת chlei
sharet could be
sold, and therefore its- its קדושה kedusha is not as fixed as
that of a קרבן, korban, and therefore it could lose its קדושה
kedusha through מעילה. me'ilah. The response could have said I disagree with
you in principle. I think a כלי שרת chlei sharet can't be
sold and it retains it. But תוספות Tosafot says that's not the
response. The response presumably also agrees כלי שרת chlei sharet could be
sold. He's just saying that it has stronger קדושה kedusha for another
reason, because since it can bestow קדושה, kedusha, it can retain its
קדושה. kedusha. So the way תוספות Tosafot reads this, it's quite interesting.
In fact we talk about a קרבן korban and כלי שרת קדושת
הגוף, chlei sharet kedushat haguf, but we never really talk about can
you sell a כלי שרת? chlei sharet? Can the בית המקדש Beis
HaMikdash sell a כלי שרת? chlei sharet? So תוספות Tosafot wants to
say the answer is yes, and therefore maybe it can lose its
קדושה. kedusha. On the other hand, it has a קדושת הגוף kedushat
haguf and it bestows קדושה kedusha on other things, and therefore maybe
it does not and it retains its קדושה kedusha and that's what's
being argued. Charlie, you had a question.
So if on סוכות Succos I take a כלי שרת, chlei sharet,
I fill it with water and I drink the water. Yes. I
can make two acts of מעילה. me'ilah. One in the כלי kli
and one in the water.
Right? Presumably, yeah. I think that that's correct.
Okay, one quick point. Yes. So רבי נחמיה, Rebbe Nechemya, at least
according to the פשט pshat of the גמרא, Gemara, learns it from
קל וחומר, kal v'chomer, but then I thought we have אין עונשין
מן הדין ein onshin min hadin kind of thing, right?
Yeah, but that's- אין עונשין מן הדין ein onshin min hadin is
when you learn the whole prohibition from a קל וחומר. kal v'chomer.
I mean if you were to say that, then we couldn't learn
any details from a קל וחומר kal v'chomer when we're dealing with
לאווין, lavin, which isn't true. The parameters we can figure out by
קל וחומר. kal v'chomer. We don't figure out the basic, like to
apply it to a new category.
You're saying that applying it to כלי שרת chlei sharet is just
a new category. You're saying it's sort of like,
yeah, saying what are the parameters of, right, yeah. Okay, so let's
take a look. Now we go on to the last line of
the משנה. Mishna. רבי אומר Rabbi omer: כל דבר שאין לו פדיון
לאלתר. kol davar she'ein lo pidyon l'altar. So רבי Rebbi seems to
be restating what the משנה Mishna said. If it can't be redeemed,
of course we just questioned whether כלי שרת chlei sharet can be
redeemed, so maybe that's- you know, maybe that's exactly the debate. Maybe
he's going back to בהמה. behemah. But anyway, let's see what the
גמרא Gemara does. Because that seems to be the same idea, בהמה
וכלי שרת. behemah u'chlei sharet. So the גמרא Gemara says היינו תנא
קמא. hainu Tanna Kamma. That's what we just said. So אמר רבא,
amar Rava, איכא בינייהו עצים. ika beiniyahu etzim. No, there's a case
where they would debate. Now what the גמרא's Gemara going to do
is going to say the debate of רבי Rebbe and the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is not really about the parameters of מעילה, me'ilah,
it's about
some detail about whether in this particular case, how to define this
object. So let's take a look. דתנו רבנן, De'tanu rabanan, האומר הרי
עלי עצים, ha'omer harei alai etzim, if somebody says I'm going to
give wood to the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. לא יפחות משני גזירין,
lo yifchos mi'shnei gezirin, it has to be two logs. That's the
first opinion. But presumably what you do is you donate the logs
for the fire. רבי אומר עצים קרבן הן וטעוני מלח. Rebbe omer
etzim korban hen v'te'uni melach. He says if you say you're going
to give... In this particular case, how to define this object? So
let's take a look. תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan. האומר הרי עלי עצים.
Ha-omer harei alai etzim. If somebody says I'm going to give wood
to the בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, לא יפחות משני גזירים, lo yifkhos
mishnei gezirim, it has to be two logs. That's the first opinion.
But presumably what you do is you donate the logs for the
fire. רבי Rebbe אומר, omer עצים קרבן הן, etzim korban hein, טעוני
מלח. te'unei melach. He says if you say you're going to give
wood logs, that means you're going to give—now the question is where's
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash ever going to get logs that they
don't use on the fire? So okay, I don't know, but that's
not our סוגיא sugya right now. You say you're going to give
logs, you're going to offer up logs as a type of an
offering, which is by the way a fascinating idea that's what we
learn from the concept of מנחה mincha that you can donate grain
offerings is that there might be other types of things that you
can offer as offerings on the מזבח mizbeach that are not mentioned
in the פסוקים, pesukim, which is like wild, who would have imagined
that? So Rabbi says that that even includes wood and you can
it become can become a קרבן korban and now we're going to
draw out the conclusions. So first of all you have to put
salt on it because you put salt on קרבנות, korbanot, וטעונין—this ve-te'unin
גירסא girsa is תנופה, tenufa, but the better גירסא is הגשה hagasha
because we're going it from מנחה. mincha. So what do you do
with a מנחה? mincha? You touch it to the מזבח, mizbeach, so
you touch the wood to the מזבח. mizbeach. It's a type of
a מנחה. mincha. מנחה mincha is a offering of inanimate objects not
limited to grain. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, so that's what he says.
So אמר רבא Amar Rava now to end that point, לדברי רבי
עצים טעונין עצים. ledivrei Rabbi etzim te'unin etzim. If you offer wood
you have to burn it on wood, so again who's giving that
wood? It's like, you know, what's that story, turtles all the way
down. So it's wood all the way down,
somebody's got to give the wood. Anyway, but maybe the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash has its own forest. ואמר רב פפא, Va'amar Rav Papa,
לדברי רבי עצים צריכין קמיצה. ledivrei Rabbi etzim t'richin kemitza. Yeah, you
have to chop it up so that you can do קמיצה, kemitza,
the handbreadth, you have to treat it like a מנחה. mincha. So
this is a very bizarre idea which we do not we don't
have time to discuss. Anyway, we did it in מנחות Menachos of
course. You all remember that one we did it in מנחות. Menachos.
Anyway, Mike helps us. Anyway, how is that relevant here? So it's
relevant here because again, we're saying, oh, they don't debate parameters of
מעילה. meila. They just debate what would happen if somebody said I'm
giving עצים. etzim. So the תנא קמא tanna kamma would say okay,
that's just בדק הבית, bedek habayis, we therefore there you know אין
מעילה אחר מעילה, ein meila achar meila, once you do it once
it's violated. Rabbi says no, I think wood is a קרבן. korban.
So according to me it's אין לו פדיון ein lo pidyon and
therefore יש מועל אחר מועל yesh mo'el achar mo'el because it's a
קרבן. korban. So they don't really debate מעילה meila questions, they debate
other particular issues. That's one answer. Let's just give the final answer.
רב פפא אמר, Rav Papa amar, קדשי מזבח תמימים ונעשו בעלי מומין
ועבר ושחטן, kodshei mizbeach temimin venasu ba'alei mumim va'avar veshachtan, איכא בינייהו.
ika beinaihu. Let's say it started as תמים, tamim, it became a
בעל מום ba'al mum and then you slaughtered it or then it
died.
We slaughtered it as a קרבן korban or just slaughtered it?
No, as doesn't matter, died, and you could just as easily have
said it died. דתניא De'tanya because we taught in a ברייתא, brayisa,
קדשי מזבח תמימים ונעשו בעלי מומין ועבר ושחטן, kodshei mizbeach temimin venasu
ba'alei mumim va'avar veshachtan, this scenario, רבי Rebbe אומר: omer יקברו, yikaveru,
you have to bury it, וחכמים אומרים: vechachamim omerim: יפדו, yifdu, you
can redeem it. What's the issue? The issue is the following. Once
it's a בעל מום ba'al mum it can be redeemed. Okay, but
if it's dead, and therefore שחיטה shechita doesn't matter, if it's dead,
then there's a question if you might remember about do things require
העמדה והערכה? ha'amada ve'ha'aracha? Do things, animals have to be alive in
order to redeem them or not? Okay, and this is the debate.
This thing is no longer קדשי מזבח, kodshei mizbeach, it's now קדשי
בדק הבית kodshei bedek habayis because it's going to be redeemed and
whatever. Anyway, so Rabbi says it requires to be alive, so you'll
have to bury it, and the חכמים chachamim say no, you can
redeem it. So according to Rabbi it doesn't have it can't be
redeemed. It's dead, it's therefore an animal needs to be alive to
be redeemed, it can't be redeemed, and therefore יש מועל אחר מועל.
yesh mo'el achar mo'el. If there's not a concept of redeeming it,
its קדושה kedusha sticks, and therefore even if you violate it the
קדושה kedusha remains and there's מועל אחר מועל. mo'el achar mo'el. Turns
to the חכמים, chachamim, you can redeem it, it's still like a
בעל מום ba'al mum or whatever and it can be redeemed, and
therefore its קדושה kedusha is not as sticky and if you would
and therefore when you violate it this dead animal there will be
it the קדושה kedusha will go away, and that is the issue
that there's מועל אחר מועל mo'el achar mo'el by מעילה. meila. You
can't do מועל mo'el twice unless we're dealing with בהמה וכלי שרת
behemah vechilei sharet where it's very much about its identity and even
when it's violated the קדושה kedusha remains.